Inventory of the Powell Family Papers 1775-1927
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Powell Famiy Papers, 1775-1927.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 65 P875
682 items and 2 manuscript volumes.
Letters and papers of the Powell family which originated in Loudoun County, Virginia, but subsequently lived in Henry [Marshall County], Illinois; Winchester, Virginia; and Alexandria, Virginia. This family of school teachers was dislocated and separated during the Civil War and lived in various locations in the state until re-uniting in Alexandria.
Powell Family,; Johns Hopkins,; Agnes Lee,; Fitzhugh Lee,; George Washington Custis Lee,; Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee,; Hunter Holmes McGuire,; James Monroe.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 682 items and 2 MsV., 1952.
Biographical/Historical Information
The central figures in this collection are Cuthbert Powell (1775-1849), his son, Charles Leven Powell (1804-1896), Charles Leven Powell's wife, Selina (Lloyd) Powell (d. 1871), and their children.
Cuthbert Powell
Cuthbert Powell (1775-1849) was born in Middleburg, Loudoun County, Virginia to parents Leven Powell (1737-1810) and Sarah (Harrison) Powell. He was one of eleven children. Cuthbert made his fortune alongside his brother, Leven Powell, Jr. (1772-1807), as a merchant and ship owner. He retired to "Llangollen," Loudoun County, Virginia in 1812 after a decline in business. Later he was elected to serve in both houses of the Virginia General Assembly; the Virginia State Senate in 1829 and the Virginia House of Delegates in 1840. In 1788, Cuthbert married Catherine Simms, daughter of Col. Charles Simms. The couple had ten children including; Anne Maria Powell (1800-1885), who married 1st cousin Dr. William Levin Powell; Dr. Llewellen Powell (1802-1870), who married cousin Sarah Elizabeth Harrison; Charles Leven Powell (1804-1896), who married Selina Lloyd; Mary Emily Powell (b.1807), who married cousin Cuthbert Powell and later Rev. George Adie; Ellen Douglas Powell (1813- 1862) who married Judge William H. Gray; Cuthbert Harrison Powell (1814-1897); and Jane Simms (Fanny) Powell, who married Wellington Gordon.
Charles Leven Powell and Family
Charles Leven Powell (1804-1896) married Selina Lloyd (d. 1871) in 1830. The couple had six children, including; Rebecca Powell (1831-1921), Harriet Lee "Hattie" (Powell) Smoot (1833-1870), Lloyd Powell (1834-1861), Charles Leven Powell, Jr. (1835-1862), Minna Powell (1837-1854), and Selina "Nina" (Powell) Hepburn (1842-1918). Harriet Lee "Hattie" (Powell) Smoot (1833-1870) married Rector Smoot. In 1871, Selina "Nina" (Powell) Hepburn (1842-1918) married Sewell Stavely Hepbron. At some point, the last name Hepbron was changed to Hepburn.
Charles Leven Powell (1804-1896) graduated from Yale College in 1825. After unsuccessful attempts at starting a law practice in Alexandria, Virginia, he was able to support his family as a teacher. Still hoping to advance his law career, the family moved to Henry, Illinois in 1850. After the death of their daughter, Minna Powell (1837-1854), the family returned to Virginia leaving the two sons behind. The parents opened a girls boarding school in Winschester, Virginia, but at the start of the Civil War in 1861 were forced to shut down. Lloyd Powell (1834-1861) returned to Virginia to enlist in the war and was killed at the 1st Battle of Bull Run, 21 July 1861. Following his death, Charles Leven Powell, Jr. (1835-1862) returned to Virginia to enlist and was killed in a skirmish in August 1862. The rest of the family scattered across the state to live with various relatives until the end of the war. The family reassembled in Alexandria, Virginia and opened another school for girls called the "Arlington Institute." The teachers on staff include Charles Leven Powell (1804-1896), his wife and his three remaining daughters. This school supported the family for 30 years until its closure in 1894.
Scope and Content Information
Letters and papers of Charles Leven Powell, his wife Selina (Lloyd) Powell and children of Loudoun County, Virginia; Henry, Illinois; Winchester, Virginia; and Alexandria, Virginia. There are also included papers of Charles Leven Powell's father, Cuthbert Powell. Prominent correspondents include Johns Hopkins, Eleanor Agnes Lee, Fitzhugh Lee, George Washington Custis Lee, Mary Anna Randolph (Custis) Lee, Hunter Holmes McGuire and James Monroe.
Letters concern Robert Young Conrad, Hunter Holmes McGuire, civilian affairs during the Civil War, the Kilpatrick-Dahlgren Raid, freedmen, Reconstruction, and the education of women. Many letters are written by women. In addition, there are a number of letters from and concerning members of the Dupuy family of Prince Edward County, Winchester, Virginia including Robert Young Conrad (president of the Virginia Secession Convention) and his son Holmes Conrad (U. S. Congressman).
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into 5 series. Series 1 contains papers of the Powell Family; Series 2 contains copies of historical letters; Series 3 contains legal papers; Series 4 contains cartes de visites; and Series 5 contains diaries, record books, and other miscellaneous volumes.
Arrangement
This collection is primarily arranged chronologically by date.
Additional Related, Separated, Bibliographic Material
Bibliography
Graydon, Katharine Virginia. Those Who Are Compelled To Be Employed: Women, Work, and Education In The Powell Family of Virginia. 1992. Master's Thesis, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Call Number: LD6051 .W5m Hist., 1992, G73
Hopkins, Frank Snowden. The Powell and Lloyd Families of Virginia. 1988. Manuscript and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Collection Number: 1889.55
Wahrsager, Kay Fierman. Network: A Sturdy of the Civil War South Through An Analysis of Letters Written By The Powell Family of Winchester, Virginia, 1861-1865. 1990. Honors Thesis, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Call Number: LD6051 .W5m Hist., 1990, W3
Related Material
Leven Powell Papers, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary; include the correspondence of Leven Powell (1737-1810), who was the father of Cuthbert Powell (1775-1849). Leven Powell served in the American Revolution, Virginia House of Delegates and U. S. House of Representatives.
Leven Powell Papers, 1774- 1806. 93 items. Collection number: Mss. 65 P87
Separated Material
Tabb-Powell Family Papers, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. Tabb-Powell Papers, 1797-1894. 1,847 items. Collection Number: Mss. 65 T14
Geographic interest includes; Alexandria, Leesburg, Winchester, and central Virginia; and Henry [Marshall County] Illinois.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Dupuy family.
Persons:
Conrad, Robert Young, 1805-1875.; Hopkins, Johns, 1795-1873.; Lee, Agnes, 1841-1873.; Lee, Fitzhugh, 1835-1905.; Lee, George Washington Custis, 1832-1913.; Lee, Mary Anna Randolph Custis, 1806- 1873.; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870.; McGuire, Hunter Holmes, 1835-1900.; Monroe, James, 1758-1831.
Subjects:
Women--United States--History- -19th century.; Freedmen--Virginia.; African Americans--Virginia--History--19th century.; Reconstruction--Virginia.; Kilpatrick-Dahlgren Raid, 1864.; United States- -History-- Civil War, 1861-1865.
Components List
  Series 1: Papers of the Powell Family
- Papers of the Powell Family, 1785-1927, n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Papers, 1785-1839., 29 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Will of Thomas Hepborn of Kent County, Maryland in which he bequeaths property to his sons John, Thomas, and Joseph, his wife Ann, and his daughters Sarah Woodall and Ann Briscoe, 19 March 1785., 2 pages. Cy of DS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Including Cy of DS, 8 April 1786, a statement by J. Nicholson that the witnesses Joshua Lamb and John Lamb (both Quakers) and Joseph Greenwood affirmed and swore that this was the last will and testament of Thomas Hepborn.
    - Hunt, Newman and Rooper [?], Porto, to Mr. Cuthbert Powell, Merchant, Alexandria, [Virginia], North America, 1 June 1813., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Reports on the status of the ship the Rising Sun; says she will dispose of her cargo as soon as possible; says the ship was detained by the British [War of 1812], but given up.
    - Legal document giving details about a case in which it was decided that Capt. George Coleman had no claim on C[uthbert?] Powell, 22 October 1813., 1 page. Cy of DS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Signed by W[illia]m Hodgson and Tho[ma]s Van Le, Jr.
    - N. Simms, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Elizabeth Trist, Birdwood, Henry Court House, Virginia, 6 February 1814., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Her daughter [?] Nancy, had a healthy baby boy who is nursing well; Nancy is staying with her now, and her husband Mr. Wallach, spends almost every night there also; is concerned that Nancy will live a hard life because of her husband's financial situation; on the other hand, her daughter Catherine [?] will be "free from the trials attended on a state of poverty," being married to [Cuthbert] Powell, who owns a large farm in Loudoun County; much Simms family news; mentions Mrs. Trist's grandson, Nicholas Trist.
    - Account of John Lloyd for tuition for Selina [(Lloyd) Powell, Cuthbert Powell's daughter-in-law], 1 October 1819., 2 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Signed by B. Cottinger.
    - Cuthbert Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Charles L. Powell, Leesburg, [Virginia], 28 November 1828., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Fatherly letter giving his opinion of a certain young lady and marriage, as well as general advice.
    - John Lloyd, Alex[andri]a, [Virginia], to C[harles] L[even] Powell, n.p., 27 December 1828., 2 pages. AcyS of L. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Discussion of his engagement to this daughter [Selina], and the seriousness of the matter, especially in concerning finances; tells of his poor financial state as related to a dowry, or the lack thereof, for his daughter; gives his approval of the "alliance," but hopes they will delay the marriage for some time.
    - James Monroe, "Oakhill", Loudoun County, [Virginia], to Burr Powell, Middleburg, Loudoun County, [Virginia], 31 December 1828., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Has given great consideration to his claim against the French government, and has turned the case over to Stephen Pleasanton, who is the auditor for the Dept. of State, and who is now handling all claims; since Mr. Pleasanton is a personal friend, and he [James Monroe] is greatly interested in his [Burr Powell] case, he knows he will get an answer soon; will also be returning the agriculture pamphlet.
    - James Monroe, "Oakhill", Loudoun County, [Virginia], to Burr Powell, Middleburg, [Virginia], 8 January 1829., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Sends extract of Mr. Pleasanton's reply concerning the claim against the French government, and asks that he reply with the necessary information; will also do anything he can to help.
    - Legal document in which Burr Powell, executor of the estate of his father Leven Powell, names Isaac Coxe Barnett, Consul at Paris, as his legal attorney in litigation process against a Rotterdam Co., Stephen Pleasonton is intermediary, 12 January 1829., 2 pages. DS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - James Monroe, "Oakhill", Loudoun County, [Virginia], to Burr Powell, Middleburg, [Virginia], 15 January 1829., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Further discussion of his claim against the French government, and dealings with Stephen Pleasanton and Issac Coxe Barnett.
    - James Monroe, "Oakhill", Loudoun County, [Virginia], to Burr Powell, Middleburg, Loudoun [sic] County, [Virginia], 20 January 1829., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      More instructions about the claim being made against the French government.
    - S[tephen] Pleasonton, Washington, [D.C.], to [James Monroe ?], n.p., 30 January 1829., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Further discussion and explanation of the case involving [Burr] Powell and his claim against the French government.
    - James Monroe, "Oakhill", Loudoun County, [Virginia], to Burr Powell, Middleburg, Loudoun [sic] County, [Virginia], 4 February 1829., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Continued information concerning Powell's claim against the French government.
    - J[oh]n J. Lloyd, Baltimore, [Maryland], to his sister, Selina Lloyd, Alexandria, D.C. [Virginia], 21 May 1829., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      The new court system has kept him extremely busy; social life has slowed down; the fashion these days to relieve boredom is to ride horseback; expresses concern for his own colt in the country; inquires after Br. Nelson and his medical career; also asks about a large, gay party at South River; recommends books for good reading including Schegel's History of Literature.
    - James Monroe, Oakhill, [Virginia], to Burr Powell, Middleburg, [Virginia], 10 August 1829., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Has received the results of his claim from Mr. Pleasanton, and regrets the outcome, which he disagrees with; does not feel anyone is to blame.
    - M[ary Anna Randolph] Custis, Arlington, [Virginia], to Selina Lloyd, Salisbury, near Centreville, Fairfax County, Virginia, 17 [?] [ante 1830]., 3 pages. ALS. Including Xcy. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Asks her to come visit over Christmas; describes the social events in Arlington; mentions her cousin George Calvert; says the big event is the fair for the benefit of orphans.
    - Selina Lloyd, "Mount Vernon", Fairfax County, [Virginia], to Charles L. Powell, Leesburg, Loudoun County, Virginia, 14 April 1830., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Describes a walk she took and the surrounding countryside, including the wildflowers and startling a herd of deer; have had many visitors, including a very graceful lady who is said to have been "addressed" by Mr. Van Buren, a "jolly goodnatured ... commodore and some of the ugliest officers," and Mrs. Porter and her scholars; tells of books she has read, including Tales of a Grandfather, The Sorcerer, and The Talisman; loving memories and looking forward to their next meeting.
    - Selina Lloyd, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Charles L. Powell, Leesburg, Loudoun County, Virginia, 9 June 1830., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Have just returned from a visit to her grandmother's and her cousin, Ann Marshall; they all are saddened by the death of Mr. Fitzhugh; describes the country from South to West River, where she had visited, and comments on meeting a lovely girl, Bella Carter; mentions the jealousy of another male [suitor?], Seldon Page; mentions Mary Custis.
    - Jno. J. Lloyd, Baltimore, [Maryland], to "sister," Selina Lloyd, Alexandria, D.C. [Virginia], 23 July 1830., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Sends his best wishes for her new life with [Charles L.] Powell; will be able to attend the wedding as well as "Brother Nelson"; is uncommonly warm; is sending a bonnet for her and a small diamond breast-pin for Father by the steamboat Franklin, commanded by Amr. Nevitt; describes the long ribbons attached to the bonnet, which are for going once all the way around the bonnet before knotting them by the ear, not for tying a bow under the chin; also includes a diagram of how to tie them in the current fashion; admits to having been helped in choosing the bonnet by Miss Olivia Donaldson.
    - Mary [Ann Randolph Custis], n.p, to Selina Lloyd, Salisbury, near Centerville, [Fairfax, Virginia], 14 [?] [ante 1830]., 4 pages. Xcy included. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Discusses events in Washington D.C.; says she went to "the President's" on New Year's day; discusses Mr. Marshall's sermons; mentions books she is reading; asks Selina to come visit her.
    - A[nn Hariotte (Lee)] Lloyd[stepmother?], n.p., to Selina Powel[l], Llangollen, Virginia, 30 November 1830., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Says her health is improving; encourages her to ask her for help when she needs it; discusses the articles she is sending her including a lemon tree, curtains, a mattress; discusses how these things will get to her; gives news about the children; Bec, Nanny, Frank, and Fred.
    - Charles L. Powell, Upperville, [Virginia], to "wife," Selina Powell, Alexandria, D.C. [Virginia], 20 March 1833., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      His mother-in-law has told him of the wonderful news of the birth of another daughter [Hattie], and that both mother and baby are safe; will be up to visit in about a week; comments on balancing the sexes in the family, and that he has "no notion of supplying my brother's and sister's children with wives"..."we shall hate to transport them [his daughters] to the wilds of the west"; all is well at home, a new hen house is being built, but the garden is too wet to work; is lonely but is visiting neighbors; family news; religious sentiments expressed about her, their new daughter, and their family.
    - Charles L. Powell, Wheeling, [West Virginia], to Selina Powell, Upperville, Fauquier County, Virginia, 4 April 1835., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Gives account of his trip to Wheeling, including a sweet good-bye from daughter Rebecca; was not able to locate Robert Gray or [?] Throckmorton at Harper's Ferry, but later met them at Point of Rocks; detailed description of a railroad and train cars; tells poignant story of a dog on the train searching for his master.
    - Selina [L. Powell], Bellefield, [Virginia], to "husband" Charles L. Powell, Louisville, Kentucky, 15-19 April 1835., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Has had many family visitors since his departure and family news; there is a measles outbreak at "Llangollen," and all of the negroes have it; she had her teeth filed by Dr. Overfield[?]; a fire in Upperville destroyed Robert Armistead's new store and the adjoining saddle shop; they have had a beautiful snowfall, covering all of the blossom-filled trees, which melted quickly, doing no harm to the fruit; had a letter from brother John, who advises that he [Charles L. Powell] "go directly to Texas"; loving stories about their daughter's activities.
    - Charles L. Powell, Upperville, [Virginia], to "wife," Selina Powell, Alexandria, D.C. [Virginia], 11 July 1835., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Had a bad thunderstorm the day she left; inquires about her trip and her relatives; details of children's activities; has let Becca sleep with him.
    - Ellen [Lloyd],"Llangollen," Loudoun County, [Virginia], to her sister Selina Powell, Louisville, Kentucky, 12 April 1836., 4 pages. ALS. Incomplete. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Their father will be taking a trip West this spring, accompanied by cousin William; family information; social life in Leesburg very quiet; misses her and her family.
    - Statement signed by Thomas Hepbron that Ezekiel F. Chambers pay Richard Lynch the sum of $44.79 for the hire of the Negro boy Pere Butler, the question having come before Thomas Hepbron, James Hepbron, and Joseph Redue, 29 December 1836., 1 page. Cy of DS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Charles L. Powell, n.p., to "wife," Selina Powell, Alexandria, D.C. [Virginia], 5 March 1839., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Details of his trip from Alexandria; spent the night with relatives; warns her about catching a cold on a windy day; tells of conversations with their young son.
  - Papers, 1840-1849., 42 items. (Box-folder 1:2-3)
    - Cuthbert Powell, Washington, [D.C.], to his son, Ch[arl]es L. Powell, Upperville, Virginia, 9 July 1841., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Private financial matters; tells of his busy schedule as a representative from Virginia. to the U.S. legislature; gives his negative opinion concerning a [bank?] bill introduced by [Henry] Clay, which he feels the President would veto; [Daniel] Webster shares his opinion; life insurance inquiry.
    - Cuthbert Powell, Washington, [D.C.], to "wife," C[atharine] Powell, Upperville, Virginia, 9 September 1841., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Will not be home when expected because the House [of Representatives] is not going to adjourn until Monday; the Congress received their second veto from President Tyler regarding the Bank Bill; describes an assault made by Sen. [Henry A.] Wise upon Sen. [Edward] Stanly in Congress.
    - Charles L. Powell, Clifton, [Virginia], to "wife," Selina Powell, Alexandria, D.C. [Virginia], 10 January 1842., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Asking about her visit to Washington and the Chamber of National Institute; speaks of floods, bad weather, but comfortable where he is, because of Margaret's[?] kindness; describes lifestyle and "humorous remarks of Charles Lamb", sexual relationship with her.
    - Cuthb[ert] Powell, Washington, [D.C.], to "wife," Catharine Powell, Upperville, Virginia, 15 June 1842., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Wishing thumb to heal; speaks of cattle and other animals at "Llangollen" that he misses; asks about children; saw Ann[?] mentions Virginia Taylor's visit; will visit wife before harvest; reference to brother, Leven, and his wife, and Sarah[?].
    - Cuthbert Powell, H[ouse] of Rep[resentatives], Washington, [D.C.], to "wife" Catharine Powell, "Llangollen," [Loudoun County, Virginia], 17 August 1842., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Hustle and excitement of the House of Representatives; hoping to adjourn on Monday the twenty-second, but difficulties cause many night meetings; political discussion about Tariff Question and Tuck bill.
    - [Catharine Powell], Llangollen, [Virginia], to "husband" [Cuthbert Powell], Washington, D.C., 24 August [1842]., 3 pages. AL. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Discusses her story at "the Springs;" tells about the politics the company there discussed; gives her own view of these issues; gives news about family and friends; hopes that Congress will soon adjourn so that he can come home.
    - Cuthbert Powell, Washington, [D.C.], to "granddaughter," Rebecca Powell, Clifton, [Virginia], 21 February 1843., 3 pages. AS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Compares episode of thief robbing hen house to thieves in Washington trying to rob "public treasures"; wants to buy books for her; tells how he wishes to be with her and the rest of his family.
    - "Mother" S[elina] Powell, Leesburg, [Virginia], to [Re]Bec[ca] Powell, n.p., 6 March [1844]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Writes of the bad weather and that they are able to get out very little; says Mr. Powell went to the Inauguration on horseback; tells what books the family members are reading; mentions the issue of white servants; discusses Rebecca's feelings of becoming a young lady; says that they could not get the house they wanted for next year; mentions Mr. Powell's feelings of frustration for not being able to better provide for them; gives more news about the Inauguration; news of family and friends.
    - Selina Powell, Leesburg, [Virginia], to Rebecca Powell, Fauquier County, Virginia, 21 August 1846., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Daughter, Harriet, left with Uncle William to spend holidays with them; daughter, Minna, had a birthday party, inviting Aunt Mary's children and Eskridges; much family news; death of Maria Lee.
    - "Daughter [Rebecca Powell], [Baltimore, Maryland?] to "Mother" [Selina Powell], n.p., 15 November [1846?]., 2 pages. AL. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Discusses her religious feelings; discusses her traveling plans; describes her relationship with each of her relatives where she is staying; says she is staying with Fan and helping her with her wedding.
    - "Mother" S[elina] Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Rebecca [Powell], n.p., 25 April [1848?]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)